# Punyajoy Saha

#### PHD STUDENT, COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur, West Bengal, India - 721302

🗷 punyajoysaha1998@gmail.com | 🌴 https://punyajoy.github.io | 🖸 punyajoy | 🛅 punyajoy-saha | 💆 @punyajoysaha

# Research Summary \_

My research lie in the intersection of computational social science and natural language processing. Currently, I am working in developing better human-in-the-loop mitigation strategies for hate speech and other forms of harmful speech like fear speech. I have experience in curating high quality social datasets and building natural language processing solutions. I am deeply interested in AI for social good.

#### Education \_\_

## Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur

PhD Computer Science and Engineering

• CGPA: 9.13; Advisor: Dr. Animesh Mukherjee; Member of CNeRG labs

• PhD Thesis: Enabling moderation of harmful content in online social media platforms

# Indian Institute of Engineering Science and Technology, Shibpur

**B.Tech Undergraduate Degree** 

• CGPA of 8.93 ; Advisor: Dr. Jaya Sil

• Computer Vision Head at Robodarshan, the robotics club of IIEST Shibpur (2017-18)

• B.Tech thesis: Application of Generative Adversarial Networks for Wallpaper Generation on Digital Devices (Link)

# Research Experiences

## **Georgia Institute of Technology**

Atlanta, United States of America

Kharagpur, West Bengal, India

Jan 2020 - present

2015 - 2019

Shibpur, Howrah, India

Jun 2023 - Sep 2023

• Was invited in the lab of Prof. Srijan Kumar's Computational Data Science Lab for the Web and Social Media

- · Worked on understanding the impact of counterspeech which is a novel to respond to hate speech
- Built a pipeline for identifying counter speech in the wild using language modelling techniques

#### **University of Hamburg**

Hamburg, Germany May 2022 - Aug 2023

RESEARCH VISITOR

RESEARCH VISITOR

• Worked with Dr. Abhik Jana and Dr. Chris Biemann in the Language Technology Group

- The first project was building a human-in-the-loop method for counterspeech generation. This pipeline is currently being used for developing a diverse counterspeech dataset.
- The second project involved understanding the intrinsic properties of language models in generation of counterspeech. We are also trying prompt based techniques to evaluate type specific counter speech generation.

#### **University of Hamburg**

Hamburg, Germany Aug 2019 - Sep 2019

RESEARCH VISITOR

• Worked with Dr. Gregor Wiedemann and Dr. Chris Biemann in the Language Technology Group

Developed the backend for Forum 4.0 project on providing a text analytics software for journalists

## Publications\_

- Roy, S., Harshavardhan, A., Mukherjee, A. and **Saha, P.**, (2023). Probing LLMs for hate speech detection: strengths and vulnerabilities. arXiv preprint arXiv:2310.12860. (accepted in EMNLP 2023)
- **Saha, P.**, Sheth, D., Kedia, K., Mathew, B., & Mukherjee, A. (2023). Rationale-Guided Few-Shot Classification to Detect Abusive Language. In Proceedings of the 26th European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (pp. 2041-2048)
- Das, M., Raj, R., **Saha, P.**, Mathew, B., Gupta, M., & Mukherjee, A. (2023). HateMM: A Multi-Modal Dataset for Hate Video Classification. Proceedings of the International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media, 17(1), 1014-1023.
- Aggarwal, P., Chawla, P., Das, M., **Saha, P.**, Mathew, B., Zesch, T. & Mukherjee, A., (2023, April). HateProof: Are Hateful Meme Detection Systems really Robust?. In Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2023 (pp. 3734-3743).
- Gupta, V., Roychowdhury, S., Das, M., Banerjee, S., **Saha, P**., Mathew, B. and Mukherjee, A., (2022). Multilingual Abusive Comment Detection at Scale for Indic Languages. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 35, pp.26176-26191.
- **Saha, P.**, Garimella K., Kalyana N.K., Pandeya S.K., Meher P., Mathew B., & Mukherjee A. (2022). On the rise of fear speech in online social media. In Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America (PNAS).

- Das, M., Dash, A., Jaiswal, S., Mathew, B., **Saha, P**. and Mukerjee, A., 2022. Platform Governance: Past, Present and Future. GetMobile: Mobile Computing and Communications, 26(1), pp.14-20.
- Saha, P., Singh, K., Kumar, A., Mathew, B., & Mukherjee, A. (2022). CounterGeDi: A controllable approach to generate polite, detoxified and emotional counterspeech. Proceedings of the Thirty-First International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (pp.5157-5163)
- Das, M., Banerjee, S., **Saha, P**. and Mukherjee, A., 2022, November. Hate Speech and Offensive Language Detection in Bengali. In Proceedings of the 2nd Conference of the Asia-Pacific Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 12th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (pp. 286-296).
- Das, M., **Saha, P.**, Dutt, R., Goyal, P., Mukherjee, A., & Mathew, B. (2021, August). You too brutus! trapping hateful users in social media: Challenges, solutions & insights. In Proceedings of the 32nd ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media (pp. 79-89).
- Mathew, B., **Saha, P.**, Yimam, S. M., Biemann, C., Goyal, P., & Mukherjee, A. (2021, May). Hatexplain: A benchmark dataset for explainable hate speech detection. In Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (Vol. 35, No. 17, pp. 14867-14875).
- **Saha, P.**, Mathew, B., Garimella, K., & Mukherjee, A. (2021, April). "Short is the Road that Leads from Fear to Hate": Fear Speech in Indian WhatsApp Groups. In Proceedings of the Web Conference 2021 (pp. 1110-1121).
- Aluru, S. S., Mathew, B., **Saha, P.**, & Mukherjee, A. (2020, September). A Deep Dive into Multilingual Hate Speech Classification. In Joint European Conference on Machine Learning and Knowledge Discovery in Databases (pp. 423-439). Springer, Cham.
- Mathew, B., **Saha, P.**, Tharad, H., Rajgaria, S., Singhania, P., Maity, S. K., & Mukherjee, A. (2019, July). Thou shalt not hate: Countering online hate speech. In Proceedings of the international AAAI conference on web and social media (Vol. 13, pp. 369-380).

# Awards, Honours & Fellowships \_\_\_\_\_

- 2023 Invited to Heidelberg Laureate Forum, HLF
  Grant accepted "Deep neural multilingual models to combat online hate content", SPARC
- 2022 Invited to Google research days, Google
- 2021 Ted Nelson Newcomer Award (Link), HyperText
  Winner of Abusive and Threatening Language Detection Task (Link), FIRE
  Winner of Offensive language shared task, DravidianLangTech
- 2020 World Rank 11 in Facebook Hatememe detection competition (Link), Meta Al
  PhD Scholarship, PMRF Rs 70,000 pm

\$ 1000

\$ 280

- 2019 1st in Offensive speech detection, HASOC
- 2018 1st in Misogynistic text classification, AMI-EVALITA

## Tutorials and Invited talks\_

Invited talk "Echoes of Fear: Unraveling the Presence of Fear Speech in Social Media Platforms." in CyberVSR'23, RIT (Link)

Tutorial on "Hate speech: Detection, Mitigation and Beyond" accepted at WSDM 2023, Singapore. (Link)

Tutorial on "Hate speech: Detection, Mitigation and Beyond" accepted at AAAI 2022 (Link).

Presented the "Fear speech in Whatsapp Groups" in Stanford Internet Observatory's End-to-end encryption Workshop

Invited talk in Understanding and Automating Counterspeech workshop, 2021 organized by CRASSH

Tutorial on "Hate speech: Detection, Mitigation and Beyond" accepted at ICWSM 2021 (Link).

Invited talk on the topic of "Generative Adversarial Network" IIEST, Shibpur, 2020 (Online).